<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Hugo Middeldorp Blog</title><link>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/</link><description>RSS feed for Hugo Middeldorp's blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Language learning tools</title><link>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/language-tools/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025</pubDate><author>Hugo Middeldorp</author><guid>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/language-tools/</guid><description>&lt;p class="first-letter:float-left first-letter:mr-2 first-letter:text-8xl mt-8">
 I have been trying to learn Turkish for some years now. My seriousness about
learning the language has fluctuated but in the last year or so, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to
take it more seriously.
&lt;/p>

&lt;p>There are countless theories and guides available online for how to learn a
language. I think the method you use doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter too much, as long as you&amp;rsquo;re
finding spending time with the language enjoyable. Ultimately, the only way you
will acquire a language is through comprehensible input.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nowadays, I&amp;rsquo;ve figured out a system that works for me and can adapt to my
varying levels of motivation, energy, and focus. The top of the of food-chain
when it comes to consumption is active listening (or reading). This is when I
will spend time after each sentence, and really try to decipher its meaning. I
will make notes of any words I don&amp;rsquo;t know, or any grammatical structures I&amp;rsquo;m
unaware of to learn later. This kind of activity takes a lot of motivation,
energy, and focus. After a long day of work, I may not have any of those. I need
an alternative for those moments: passive listening. Rather than spending time
distracted, not doing anything fulfilling, I can sit on the couch, or do some
chores, while listening to a podcast. I can still make notes every now and then
of words that seem important, but I&amp;rsquo;m not necessarily focused on understanding
everything. I&amp;rsquo;m still listening, but not actively trying to understand.
Depending on my level of motivation, energy and focus, I will pick something
appropriate on that continuum between high-focus active reading/listening, and
low-focus passive listening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However I spend time listening, I try as much as possible to not interrupt the
flow. If there is a word I don&amp;rsquo;t understand, I&amp;rsquo;ll translate it so I can keep
going, and add it to a list. Once I&amp;rsquo;ve finished my listening session, I&amp;rsquo;ll go
and add all those words to a vocabulary deck on Anki. When I&amp;rsquo;m trying to track
how much time I&amp;rsquo;m spending studying Turkish, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to count the time I&amp;rsquo;m
spending adding cards to the deck, because it&amp;rsquo;s not really time that I&amp;rsquo;m
engaging with the language; it&amp;rsquo;s more of a chore. I&amp;rsquo;ll leave it to the end so it
doesn&amp;rsquo;t distract me from my main task.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="turkish-content">Turkish content&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Here is a short list of the places I&amp;rsquo;ve gone to find Turkish content. Most of
the Turkish series I&amp;rsquo;ve watched, I haven&amp;rsquo;t liked. Even the ones I like, I would
have almost certainly not watched if they were in English.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Pera Palas&amp;rsquo;ta Gece Yarısı: fun Netflix series with time travel and some
historical drama&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aşk 101: also a fun series to watch about a group of teenagers finishing
high school. The sequences when they are adults are hard to watch (and not
really crucial to the story) but the rest of the show is fun and wholesome.
Also a lot of slang!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Terzi: was mostly interesting in the beginning for the original intrigue, but
I finished watching the series because of the availability of the language
spoken.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nasıl Olunur: podcast, I don&amp;rsquo;t really know what they are talking about; most
of the time, I&amp;rsquo;m not actively listening. The host Nilay Örnek seems like a fun
person, which makes it fun to listen to.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Kürk Mantolu Madonna: book of classic Turkish literature. I just finished
reading it and I really enjoyed the story. In terms of the language, you
really get a good idea of how poetic Turkish can be. I&amp;rsquo;ve also started reading
another book by the same author called İçimizdeki Şeytan.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/c/Bar%C4%B1%C5%9F%C3%96zcan">Barış Özcan&lt;/a> talks about technology, productivity, and science.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/@pelindilaracolak">Pelin Dilara Çolak&lt;/a> talks about philosophy.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In the beginning, I found it easy to try and look for more content streams: more
TV shows, more YouTube channels, but actually, what matters is the quality of
the content, and how much enjoyment you get out of consuming it. I could watch
the same 15-minute video for a week and still have things to learn from it. Once
you find something you like, spend time with it, don&amp;rsquo;t waste it looking for
something else.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="leverage-technology">Leverage technology&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Since I started using artificial intelligence for language learning a year ago,
its capabilities have come a long way. Here are some of the ways I use it now:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Split sentences into understandable chunks. When first starting to read, I
found it difficult to understand larger sentences. I would get ChatGPT to
split it and translate it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create example sentences for a given word. Sometimes when sentence mining,
there are too many unknown words to add it to the vocabulary deck &amp;ndash; AI is
very good at generating example sentences of varying levels using a given
word.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rephrase in simpler terms. If there is a topic that is of high interest, but
the language is too difficult, AI can reword it to make it easier to
understand.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Explain sentence structure, or grammar. The Turkish language has a fun quirk
that I was able to discover the name of thanks to AI: reduplication. It gave a
great explanation and allowed me to go and do some further research.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Provide various grammar or translation exercises.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conversation partner. At the time of writing, you still can&amp;rsquo;t speak to ChatGPT
for free, and Gemini doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel as natural to talk to, so I record my audio
in Gemini and paste it into ChatGPT.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Audio to subtitle. OpenAI has an open source library called &lt;a href="https://github.com/openai/whisper">Whisper&lt;/a> which you
can use locally, for free, to transcribe (and translate) audio from a video
and turn it into subtitles. On my computer the processing time is about the
length of the video, so I just have to prepare a bit in advance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Translation, especially when the sentences become more complex and abstract.
For this I use DeepL.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Summarisation. NotebookLM can ingest entire videos, books, textbooks and use
it as a source of knowledge. I have used it to provide chapter-by-chapter
summaries of the book that I&amp;rsquo;m reading so that I have primed myself before
reading. It&amp;rsquo;s not 100% accurate, but it&amp;rsquo;s close enough to be useful.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="optimisation">Optimisation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve found language learning to be particularly susceptible to
over-optimisation. It&amp;rsquo;s easier to think about learning a language, to learn
about learning, than it is to actually learn. There is an amount of preparation
that is required for language learning, and there is a level of optimisation
that will naturally happen as you spend more and more time learning; all this is
normal. What I am cautioning against is the trap of &lt;em>thinking&lt;/em> rather than
&lt;em>doing&lt;/em>. There is no easy way to learn a language, it&amp;rsquo;s just about time and
attention.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re finding that you&amp;rsquo;re looking for an easier way, the problem is probably
not the method, but the content. Rather than looking for another set of
vocabulary, or another course, or another textbook, try to find a book, a film,
or a YouTube channel that you enjoy reading, or watching.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s hard to measure progress in this way. There is no &amp;ldquo;levelling up&amp;rdquo;. I find
that every now and then I&amp;rsquo;ll feel discouraged by a seeming lack of progress. In
those instances, I&amp;rsquo;ll go back and read or watch something I first consumed
months ago, and I&amp;rsquo;ll often find it much easier to understand than it was the
first time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="learning-in-public">Learning in public&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Learning is difficult and solitary by nature, even language learning. Most of
us don&amp;rsquo;t have the luxury of having access to natives with infinite patience and
teaching ability. I spend a lot of time, alone, mostly in silence, learning a
language I hope to be able to communicate in some day soon.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sharing is also difficult as a learner, because what I am learning is nothing
revolutionary. I can&amp;rsquo;t really teach anyone how to understand a foreign language.
But, what I can do is share some of my first-hand experience and some of the
resources I found useful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are also learning something, no matter what it is, I would also encourage
you to share your experience and useful resources. The goal with this article
for me was to write something that would have been useful to me two years ago,
and hopefully by extension, useful to someone today!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="further-reading">Further Reading&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Here are some of the methods that have been influential in shaping my way of
learning a foreign language.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://refold.la/simplified/">https://refold.la/simplified/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Principles and Practice in Second Language Acquisition, Stephen D. Krashen &lt;a href="https://www.sdkrashen.com/content/books/principles_and_practice.pdf">https://www.sdkrashen.com/content/books/principles_and_practice.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>And here are more Turkish resources I&amp;rsquo;ve found helpful:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://turkishbasics.com/">https://turkishbasics.com/&lt;/a> A great beginner resource for basic grammar&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://tureng.com/en/turkish-english">https://tureng.com/en/turkish-english&lt;/a> Turkish/English dictionary&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.seslisozluk.net/">https://www.seslisozluk.net/&lt;/a> Another dictionary I used in the beginning, I
have replaced it with tureng now&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://turkishtextbook.com/">https://turkishtextbook.com/&lt;/a> Textbook with progressive grammar and lots of
real-world examples&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://kitapcumhuriyeti.net/">https://kitapcumhuriyeti.net/&lt;/a> PDF books for free&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.trtdinle.com/">https://www.trtdinle.com/&lt;/a> I&amp;rsquo;ve used it for audiobooks, but it has other audio
content&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://youglish.com/turkish">https://youglish.com/turkish&lt;/a> To help with pronunciation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="header-image">Header Image&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Interior With a Girl Reading&lt;/em>, Carl Holsøe (&lt;a href="https://open.smk.dk/en/artwork/image/kms1790">link&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why teach music</title><link>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/why-teach-music/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025</pubDate><author>Hugo Middeldorp</author><guid>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/why-teach-music/</guid><description>&lt;p class="first-letter:float-left first-letter:mr-2 first-letter:text-8xl mt-8">
 I have always suffered from a case of
&lt;em>trying-to-do-too-many-things-all-the-time&lt;/em>. Ever since I finished university,
there have always been more projects on my to-do list than I could ever handle.
While I changed careers and I am no longer a teacher, I still feel a burning
need to share the insights I&amp;rsquo;ve gathered through my years of learning and
teaching piano. (Maybe there is some sense of grandiose importance &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;m not
going to concern myself with a psychoanalysis).
&lt;/p>

&lt;p>Among many other reasons (excuses) I&amp;rsquo;ve found to &lt;em>not&lt;/em> work on this project is
the lack of justification I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to provide myself for spending time on
this. I changed careers to try and have a greater positive impact and now I want
to revert back and go write a piano book online? What is the thinking here?
While I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced that answering this will suddenly make me write the
whole book in one sitting, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping the answer has a freeing effect and I hope
others can benefit from the same mentality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I get a lot of enjoyment out of music. I enjoy playing it and I enjoy listening
to it. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe we are brought into being for a purpose. There is no
inherent meaning to life. We create it by maximising the amount of time we can
get fulfilment. For my own selfish pleasure, I want there to be amazing
musicians, composers and performers for my listening pleasure. I can also
appreciate that some percentage of the population would love nothing more in the
world than to be an amazing musician, composer or performer (I used to be one
such person).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my experience, finding good music learning material is difficult. Not for the lack
of resources (we have more of those than we could ever wish for), but for the
lack of clear pedagogical methods. Becoming a great musician is difficult enough
to do, if one also has to find their own educational resources, and make their
own curriculum, a lot of energy and effort are diverted from learning an
instrument.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is sad because it means that somewhere, there is someone willing to put in
the work who doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the correct resources. What a waste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I spent a lot of time practising and learning about music. I also spent a lot of
time trying to improve as a teacher. Now that I have left that career, it would
be a shame for all that experience and knowledge to go to waste. I must share
it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That is why teaching music (or anything for that matter) is important. Knowledge
takes time to acquire, the internet provides unrivalled access to learning
resources, and I have developed ideas and opinions that I think are worth
sharing. I want to hear more great musicians, I want to help musicians learn and
do what they love, to thrive even if they live in a rural area with little to no
opportunity or access to a great teacher.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I need to do my part, no matter how small, to make music education better.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>This article was written months ago, and for some reason I can&amp;rsquo;t explain, was
never published. I&amp;rsquo;m happy to announce that after writing this article, I
finished writing the book. It is available for free &lt;a href="https://learnpianothehardway.com/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="header-image">Header Image&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Wife of a homesteader with her WPA (Work Projects Administration) music class,
Lee Russell (&lt;a href="https://www.loc.gov/item/2017786755/">link&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Do what is difficult</title><link>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/do-what-is-difficult/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024</pubDate><author>Hugo Middeldorp</author><guid>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/do-what-is-difficult/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;There is no great credit in behaving bravely in times of prosperity.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>Seneca, Of Consolation: To Marcia (V)&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p class="first-letter:float-left first-letter:mr-2 first-letter:text-8xl mt-8">
 Comfort is one of the great luxuries of modern life. In the last hundred years, things have gotten more efficient, more reliable, faster and easier. Innovation has largely been driven by a want to make things easier. While this trend has improved our lives in many aspects, I think we would benefit from introducing difficulty back in.
We have gotten &lt;em>too&lt;/em> comfortable, and that has made us fragile.
&lt;/p>

&lt;p>When we don&amp;rsquo;t use our muscles, they start to deteriorate. We need to keep them active, put them through strain to keep them working.
Similar to our body, our mind also deteriorates with time. I didn&amp;rsquo;t do any maths while I was at university (I studied music); and when I got into computer science some years later, I found that my algebra had almost completely gone, even though I used to be quite good at it.
Everything trends towards chaos. Things don&amp;rsquo;t just stay the same; if left alone, they get worse in time. It takes effort to keep things ordered and working.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I want to live a good life and be a good person. For me that means showing kindness, patience, courage, discipline and curiosity. These are the virtues that I want to embody, that is the kind of person I want to be.
Virtues are a pattern of behaviour, that is to say they&amp;rsquo;re a habit. And just like any other habit, virtues need to be practised regularly to upkeep and to improve.
While I get the opportunity to practise kindness and patience every day, I can&amp;rsquo;t say the same about courage and discipline.
So what happens when you rarely have to show courage, strength, or discipline?
What does it mean to be brave when you don&amp;rsquo;t have any fears to face? What does it mean to be courageous when you are never presented with any adversity?
Discipline, courage, strength can only be displayed, and are only useful when faced with difficult challenges. If you&amp;rsquo;re never in the situation where it&amp;rsquo;s needed, how do you know you have it?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Difficulty used to be a fact of life, now it&amp;rsquo;s a choice. What&amp;rsquo;s amazing about the time that we&amp;rsquo;re living in now is that we get to choose what comforts we want, and the ones we want to reject. We can figure out the minimum comfort that we need and throw away the rest.
It can be difficult to find the right balance of difficulty. I find that the worst periods of my life have either come from way too much difficulty, or too little.
When we have the luxury of choice, we need to choose what is difficult because it&amp;rsquo;s what keeps us strong.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Take a good look at your life, your habits, your possessions and get rid of all that isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary.
I&amp;rsquo;m not saying you should go out and start arguments with everyone to build your ability to handle conflicts. That would contradict another virtue you&amp;rsquo;re trying to harbour of being nice &amp;ndash; which I think is probably more important day-to-day. I&amp;rsquo;m not suggesting you should go out and do incredibly risky things to prove to yourself that you&amp;rsquo;re courageous. Risking your life every weekend doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like a particularly productive use of your time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We need to be realistic about the kinds of situations we&amp;rsquo;re going to find ourselves in. We also need to be realistic about the kind of challenges we can overcome. What is difficult for someone can be trivial for another.
My brother was terrified of spiders, me not so much. When there were any spiders at the house, I would be tasked with getting rid of them. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t pleasant but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the worse. I am not braver than my brother for getting rid of the spider.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You need to do what is difficult &lt;em>for you&lt;/em>. There is no point in comparing yourself to others there.
Whenever I have to make a decision about anything, I consider the question: &amp;ldquo;What is more difficult?&amp;rdquo; If the more difficult option doesn&amp;rsquo;t come with major disadvantages (e.g., takes a lot longer, is very painful, costs more) then I will choose that.
Maybe a better framing is &amp;ldquo;Do what is uncomfortable&amp;rdquo; but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound as catchy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This article is more of a plea to myself to do what is difficult, as I&amp;rsquo;m writing it, I am solidifying the importance of this idea and I&amp;rsquo;m finding more aspects of my life when I can apply this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Do what is difficult. Seek discomfort. Reject complacency.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="further-reading">Further Reading&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Of Consolation: To Marcia&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; Seneca, 40 AD (&lt;a href="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Of_Consolation:_To_Marcia">link&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="header-image">Header Image&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Blacksmith, George Jones (&lt;a href="https://collections.britishart.yale.edu/catalog/tms:10720">link&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>