<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Hugo Middeldorp Blog</title><link>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/</link><description>RSS feed for Hugo Middeldorp's blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-uk</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why teach music</title><link>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/why-teach-music/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025</pubDate><author>Hugo Middeldorp</author><guid>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/why-teach-music/</guid><description>&lt;p class="first-letter:float-left first-letter:mr-2 first-letter:text-8xl mt-8">
 I have always suffered from a case of
&lt;em>trying-to-do-too-many-things-all-the-time&lt;/em>. Ever since I finished university,
there have always been more projects on my to-do list than I could ever handle.
While I changed careers and I am no longer a teacher, I still feel a burning
need to share the insights I&amp;rsquo;ve gathered through my years of learning and
teaching piano. (Maybe there is some sense of grandiose importance &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;m not
going to concern myself with a psychoanalysis).
&lt;/p>

&lt;p>Among many other reasons (excuses) I&amp;rsquo;ve found to &lt;em>not&lt;/em> work on this project is
the lack of justification I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to provide myself for spending time on
this. I changed careers to try and have a greater positive impact and now I want
to revert back and go write a piano book online? What is the thinking here?
While I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced that answering this will suddenly make me write the
whole book in one sitting, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping the answer has a freeing effect and I hope
others can benefit from the same mentality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I get a lot of enjoyment out of music. I enjoy playing it and I enjoy listening
to it. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe we are brought into being for a purpose. There is no
inherent meaning to life. We create it by maximising the amount of time we can
get fulfilment. For my own selfish pleasure, I want there to be amazing
musicians, composers and performers for my listening pleasure. I can also
appreciate that some percentage of the population would love nothing more in the
world than to be an amazing musician, composer or performer (I used to be one
such person).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my experience, finding a good music education is difficult. Not for the lack
of resources (we have more of those than we could ever wish for), but for the
lack of clear pedagogical methods. Becoming a great musician is difficult enough
to do, if one also has to find their own educational resources, and make their
own curriculum, a lot of energy and effort are diverted from learning an
instruments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is sad because it means that somewhere, there is someone willing to put in
the work who doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the correct resources. What a waste.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I spent a lot of time practising and learning about music. I also spent a lot of
time trying to improve as a teacher. Now that I have left that career, it would
be a shame for all that experience and knowledge to go to waste. I must share
it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That is why teaching music (or anything for that matter) is important. Knowledge
takes time to acquire, the internet provides unrivalled access to learning
resources, and I have developed ideas and opinions that I think are worth
sharing. I want to hear more great musicians, I want to help musicians learn and
do what they love, to thrive even if they live in a rural area with little to no
opportunity or access to a great teacher.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I need to do my part, no matter how small, to make music education better.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>This article was written months ago, and for some reason I can&amp;rsquo;t explain, was
never published. I&amp;rsquo;m happy to announce that after writing this article, I
finished writing the book. It is available for free &lt;a href="https://learnpianothehardway.com/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="header-image">Header Image&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Wife of a homesteader with her WPA (Work Projects Administration) music class,
Lee Russell (&lt;a href="https://www.loc.gov/item/2017786755/">link&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Do what is difficult</title><link>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/do-what-is-difficult/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024</pubDate><author>Hugo Middeldorp</author><guid>https://hugomiddeldorp.com/posts/do-what-is-difficult/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;There is no great credit in behaving bravely in times of prosperity.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>Seneca, Of Consolation: To Marcia (V)&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p class="first-letter:float-left first-letter:mr-2 first-letter:text-8xl mt-8">
 Comfort is one of the great luxuries of modern life. In the last hundred years, things have gotten more efficient, more reliable, faster and easier. Innovation has largely been driven by a want to make things easier. While this trend has improved our lives in many aspects, I think we would benefit from introducing difficulty back in.
We have gotten &lt;em>too&lt;/em> comfortable, and that has made us fragile.
&lt;/p>

&lt;p>When we don&amp;rsquo;t use our muscles, they start to deteriorate. We need to keep them active, put them through strain to keep them working.
Similar to our body, our mind also deteriorates with time. I didn&amp;rsquo;t do any maths while I was at university (I studied music); and when I got into computer science some years later, I found that my algebra had almost completely gone, even though I used to be quite good at it.
Everything trends towards chaos. Things don&amp;rsquo;t just stay the same; if left alone, they get worse in time. It takes effort to keep things ordered and working.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I want to live a good life and be a good person. For me that means showing kindness, patience, courage, discipline and curiosity. These are the virtues that I want to embody, that is the kind of person I want to be.
Virtues are a pattern of behaviour, that is to say they&amp;rsquo;re a habit. And just like any other habit, virtues need to be practised regularly to upkeep and to improve.
While I get the opportunity to practise kindness and patience every day, I can&amp;rsquo;t say the same about courage and discipline.
So what happens when you rarely have to show courage, strength, or discipline?
What does it mean to be brave when you don&amp;rsquo;t have any fears to face? What does it mean to be courageous when you are never presented with any adversity?
Discipline, courage, strength can only be displayed, and are only useful when faced with difficult challenges. If you&amp;rsquo;re never in the situation where it&amp;rsquo;s needed, how do you know you have it?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Difficulty used to be a fact of life, now it&amp;rsquo;s a choice. What&amp;rsquo;s amazing about the time that we&amp;rsquo;re living in now is that we get to choose what comforts we want, and the ones we want to reject. We can figure out the minimum comfort that we need and throw away the rest.
It can be difficult to find the right balance of difficulty. I find that the worst periods of my life have either come from way too much difficulty, or too little.
When we have the luxury of choice, we need to choose what is difficult because it&amp;rsquo;s what keeps us strong.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Take a good look at your life, your habits, your possessions and get rid of all that isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary.
I&amp;rsquo;m not saying you should go out and start arguments with everyone to build your ability to handle conflicts. That would contradict another virtue you&amp;rsquo;re trying to harbour of being nice &amp;ndash; which I think is probably more important day-to-day. I&amp;rsquo;m not suggesting you should go out and do incredibly risky things to prove to yourself that you&amp;rsquo;re courageous. Risking your life every weekend doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like a particularly productive use of your time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We need to be realistic about the kinds of situations we&amp;rsquo;re going to find ourselves in. We also need to be realistic about the kind of challenges we can overcome. What is difficult for someone can be trivial for another.
My brother was terrified of spiders, me not so much. When there were any spiders at the house, I would be tasked with getting rid of them. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t pleasant but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the worse. I am not braver than my brother for getting rid of the spider.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You need to do what is difficult &lt;em>for you&lt;/em>. There is no point in comparing yourself to others there.
Whenever I have to make a decision about anything, I consider the question: &amp;ldquo;What is more difficult?&amp;rdquo; If the more difficult option doesn&amp;rsquo;t come with major disadvantages (e.g., takes a lot longer, is very painful, costs more) then I will choose that.
Maybe a better framing is &amp;ldquo;Do what is uncomfortable&amp;rdquo; but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound as catchy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This article is more of a plea to myself to do what is difficult, as I&amp;rsquo;m writing it, I am solidifying the importance of this idea and I&amp;rsquo;m finding more aspects of my life when I can apply this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Do what is difficult. Seek discomfort. Reject complacency.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="further-reading">Further Reading&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Of Consolation: To Marcia&lt;/em> &amp;ndash; Seneca, 40 AD (&lt;a href="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Of_Consolation:_To_Marcia">link&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="header-image">Header Image&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Blacksmith, George Jones (&lt;a href="https://collections.britishart.yale.edu/catalog/tms:10720">link&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>